Guide to the African-Americans In Film: Collection Of Press Books, Campaign Books, Advertising Manuals, Etc., 1919-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
African-Americans In Film: Collection Of Press Books, Campaign Books, Advertising Manuals, Etc. 1919-2000
0.3 linear feet Extent: 247 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00030
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The African-Americans In Film: Collection Of Press Books, Campaign Books, Advertising Manuals, Etc. was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2001, 2009, 2010, 2014.
Collection Overview
The 196 films represented by this collection of movie promotional and advertising materials cover a variety of types of motion pictures, from obscure Black-cast silent films by the Norman Film Manufacturing Company, to movies with supporting and starring roles for African-Americans and modern Black-cast films. The collection includes representative coverage of legendary film artists such as Dorothy Dandridge and Sidney Poitier, and more comprehensive coverage of the classic era of Blaxploitation films, the 1970s.
The collection contains 247 separate press books, campaign books, advertising manuals, supplements and other ephemeral promotional booklets, broadsides or single sheet publications, and posters designed for the use of theater distributors, dating from the independent Black films of the 1920s to 2000. The collection also includes some souvenir program booklets sold at theaters, and two published hardcover books.
Press books are no longer made. They were often extremely elaborate and profusely illustrated, containing many diverse articles about the film, the stars and the filmmakers, as well as ad mattes for proposed publicity campaigns, detailed plot synopses, cast and crew credits, etc. Also featured are small versions of posters available to local theaters. The ad campaigns alone provide a great deal of information about how the actors, directors, and films were promoted in the press and in theater displays. Virtually everything contained in this collection is ephemeral in nature. Even the more recent press kits were never publicly distributed or sold, and are also scarce, possibly unique.
Unless otherwise noted, all the promotional pieces in this collection are of U.S. origin. A few items from Great Britain, Denmark, Japan, Germany and France add a multi-cultural perspective.
The inventory, as well as the physical arrangement of the collection, is alphabetical by film title, with numerical titles first and all initial articles ignored. Each inventory entry includes the film title (as it appears in the promotional material), the date of the film (according to the entry in the Internet Movie Database), the size designation (12mo, 4to, 8vo or Folio), and the number of pages and/or leaves of the promotional material.
Additional information appears in many but not all of the inventory entries. Some entries include a designation for the type of material, e.g., press book, advertising supplement, promotional booklet, theater program, press book insert, etc. while some entries include a copyright date for the material (especially when this date differs from the film's date). Many entries include the names of one or more of the African-American actors, actresses, singers, directors, screenplay authors or producers involved with the film; however, such lists are selective, not comprehensive. A substantial number of the entries in the inventory also include descriptive comments by the dealer, George Robert Minkoff Inc., and quotes or references selected by the dealer from the following sources: Bogle = Bogle, Donald. Blacks in American films and television: an encyclopedia. Bogle II = Bogle, Donald. Toms, coons, mulattoes, mammies, and bucks: an interpretive history of Blacks in American films.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
African Americans in motion pictures; African American women in motion pictures; Advertising -- Motion pictures; Motion pictures -- Marketing; African American motion picture actors and actresses; African Americans in the motion picture industry; African American motion picture producers and directors; Blaxploitation films; Race relations in motion pictures; Motion pictures -- United States; Motion pictures -- Distribution; Motion picture industry -- United States; Ephemera; Norman Film Manufacturing Company; John Hope Franklin Collection of African and African-American Documentation
Contents of Collection
- Numeric film titles and film titles A-C (Box 1)
  - 48 Hours, 1982. French press book., (4to, 2 p.)
    Eddie Murphy. Bogle, p. 85-6.
  - A.K.A. Cassius Clay, 1970., (Folio, 2 p.)
    Feature about the legendary boxer Muhammad Ali.
  - Airport '77, 1977. British advertising promotion guide sheet., (8vo, 2 p.)
  - Airport '77, 1977. Press book., (8vo, 14 p.)
    Robert Hooks.
  - All the Young Men, 1960. Advertising supplement., (Folio, 2 p.)
    Publicity specifically designed for Black audiences.
  - Amazing Grace, 1974. Press book., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Moms Mabley. Stepin Fetchit. Bogle, p. 12: Mabley's a legend long past her prime but a legend captured on celluloid nonetheless.
  - American Gigolo, 1980., (8vo, 20 p.)
    Bill Duke as a sinister pimp, a few years before he commenced his career as a director.
  - American Gigolo, 1980. British press kit., (8vo, 4+1 p.)
  - Amistad, 1997. Japanese promotional booklet., (4to, 24 p.)
    Djimon Hounsou.
  - Angel Levine, The, 1970., (4to, 6 p.)
    Harry Belafonte produced and starred in this adaptation of Bernard Malamud.
  - Angels in the Outfield, 1994. Promotional booklet, Preview spring 1994., (8vo, 12 p.)
    Sent out by Disney and containing an article about Danny Glover and the film.
  - Another 48 Hrs., 1990. Japanese promotional brochure., (4to, 24 p.)
    Eddie Murphy.
  - Bamboozled, 2000., (2 Posters)
    Spike Lee directed this film about a frustrated African American TV writer who proposes a blackface minstrel show in protest, but it becomes a hit, to his chagrin. Starring Damon Wayans, Savion Glover, Jada Pinkett Smith and Tommy Davidson.
  - Big Doll House, The, 1971., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Pam Grier in one of her early starring roles.
  - Billy Jack, 1971., (4to, 12 p.)
  - Billy Jack, 1971. British press kit., (4to, 4 p. + 3 leaves + 1 leaf + 2 p.)
  - Bird, 1988. French press sheet., (4to, 2 p.)
    Clint Eastwood directed this biography of the legendary Charlie Parker, who was portrayed by Forest Whitaker.
  - Black Belt Jones, 1974. Press book., (4to. 12 p.)
    Jim Kelly. Scatman Crothers. Bogle, p. 22: Fighting the mob to save a Black self-defense school in Watts...Sometimes technically inept, sometimes embarrassingly written, sometimes just plain foolish, Black Belt Jones is also sometimes surprising fun: it's popcorn, comic-strip entertainment that moves swiftly.
  - Black Belt Jones, 1974. Promotional booklet done like a comic book., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Black Caesar, 1973., (4to. 20 p.)
    Fred Williamson.
  - Black Girl, 1972. Press book., (4to, 9 leaves)
    Ossie Davis (director). Leslie Uggams. Ruby Dee. Bogle, p. 23-4: Seldom has this kind of drama about the problems and predicaments peculiar to Black women...reached American films.
  - Black Gold, 1927., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Black-cast drama about oil-drilling from the Norman Film Manufacturing Company.
  - Black Mama, White Mama, 1972., (4to, 16 p.)
    Pam Grier.
  - Black Rodeo, 1972. Press book., (4to, 8 leaves)
    Rodeo documentary, with guest appearances by Muhammad Ali and Woody Strode.
  - Black Shampoo, 1976., (6 p.)
    Blaxploitation film starring John Daniels and Tanya Boyd.
  - Blazing Stewardesses, 1974., (Folio, 6 p.)
  - Book of Numbers, 1973., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Raymond St. Jacques. Bogle, p. 34.
  - Bronco Billy, 1980. Special promotional booklet., (4to, 8 p.)
    Synopses in English, Spanish, French, German and Italian.
  - Bronze Venus, 1943; reissue of 1938 film The Duke is Tops., (Folio, 4 p., fragile at folds.)
    Lena Horne's debut film and a very rare specimen of Black independent filmmaking. Bogle, p. 76: Lena, as a wide-eyed and rather pepped-up young singer, displayed a natural, fresh quality rarely seen in many of her later Hollywood films when she often came across as an overly controlled ice maiden. Lena's co-star is former bandleader Ralph Cooper, who was also one of the founders of Million Dollar Productions, a company that made all-Black films in the 1930s and early 1940s.
  - Brubaker, 1980. British press book., (8vo, 8 p.)
  - Brubaker, 1980. Press book., (8vo, 41 leaves)
    Yaphet Kotto.
  - Bull-Dogger, The, 1921.
    See entry for Love Bug, The. 1919.
  - Burn! 1970., (Folio, 18 p.)
    Film directed by Gillo Pontecorvo about a slave revolt on a Caribbean island early in the 19th century. Bogle, p. 141.
  - Bus is Coming, The, 1971., (4to, 8 p.)
    Mike Sims. Bogle II, p. 241.
  - Can't Stop the Music, 1980. Campaign press book., (Folio, 32 p.)
    Alex Briley. Ray Simpson.
  - Cardinal, The, 1963., (Folio, 18 p.)
    Ossie Davis portrays a Southern Roman Catholic priest whose church has been burned by the KKK.
  - Carmen Jones, 1954. Danish theater program, (12mo, 16 p.)
    Program is extensively illustrated.
  - Celebration at Big Sur, 1971. Press book., (4to, 8 p.)
    Dorothy Morrison. The Combs Sisters.
  - Chain Gang Women, 1971., (Folio, 8 p.)
  - Change of Mind, 1969. Ad supplement, (4to, 4 p.)
  - Change of Mind, 1969., (4to, 8 leaves, 4 p.)
    Raymond St. Jacques. The brain of a white district attorney is transplanted into the body of a Black man.
  - Charley-One-Eye, 1972. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Richard Roundtree in a Blaxploitation western.
  - Chase for the Golden Needles, 1974. Campaign manual., (4to, 4 p.)
    Jim Kelly.
  - Checkerboard, 1959. Exhibitor's manual., (Folio, 6 p.)
    American release of the French film Les Tripes Au Soleil, a film whose setting is unclear (it seems to be a French film set in the Old West), with the cast equally divided between Black and white actors.
  - Claudine, 1974. Press book., (4to, 6 leaves, 4 p.)
    James Earl Jones. Diahann Carroll. Bogle, p. 54-56: A 1970s new-style Black romantic comedy/drama that is occasionally too calculating, often synthetic and rather hokey, but mostly entertaining and diverting.
  - Clay Pigeon, 1971. Exhibitor's campaign book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Ivan Dixon.
  - Cleopatra Jones, 1973. Press book., (4to, 14 p.)
    Tamara Dobson. Bogle, p. 57: Glamorous, statuesque, sophisticated, and surprisingly sweet-tempered and unassuming, Dobson is a delectable comic-strip heroine come true.
  - Cleopatra Jones and the Casino of Gold, 1975. Press book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Tamara Dobson. Bogle, p. 58: Example of the kind of Black macho mama movie that proved popular with audiences of the mid-1970s.
  - Coffy, 1973., (4to, 16 p.)
    Pam Grier. Bogle, p. 58: simple-minded, violent, bloody, and a technical mess, this is the film nonetheless that made Pam Grier a B-movie star.
  - Color Purple, 1985. Exhibitor's campaign book (British press book), (8vo, 6 p.)
    Alice Walker adaptation.
  - Come Back, Charleston Blue, 1972. Press book., (4to, 14 p.)
    Godfrey Cambridge. Raymond St. Jacques. This is a sequel to Cotton Comes to Harlem, adapted, like its precursor, from Chester Himes.
  - Condor, El, 1970., (4to, 20 p.)
    Jim Brown. Bogle II, p. 220.
  - Cool Breeze, 1972. Press book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Pam Grier. Thalmus Rasulala.
  - Cotton Club, 1984. Japanese promotional brochure, (4to, 36 p.)
    Gregory Hines.
  - Crimson Skull, 1921., (Folio, 4 p.)
    From the Norman Film Manufacturing Company: Baffling Western Mystery Photo-Play. Supported by Bill Pickett, World's Champion Wild West Performer, the one-legged Marvel, Steve Reynolds, and 30 Colored Cowboys. Produced in the All-Colored City of Boley, Okla. An Epic of Wild Life and Smoking Revolvers. All-Colored Cast. Contains an article by star Anita Bush, Introduction of Negro Drama in New York.
  - Crimson Skull, 1921.
    [See entry for Love Bug, The (1919)]
- Film titles D-K (Box 2)
  - Dark of the Sun, 1968., (Folio, 16 p.)
    Jim Brown in one of his early starring roles in this action film.
  - Decks Ran Red, The, 1958. Press book., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Dorothy Dandridge. Bogle, p. 72: Her role is an unusual one for a Black actress. Simply stated, she plays the only woman aboard a shipload of hearty, lusty, red-blooded males.
  - Defiant Ones, The, 1958. Press book., (Folio, 20 p.)
    Sidney Poitier in what was almost certainly his breakthrough role in this saga of interracial bonding. Bogle, p. 73-4: Definitely broke new ground and it firmly established Poitier as a major American film star.
  - Demolition Man, 1993. Japanese promotional booklet., (8vo, 24 p.)
    Wesley Snipes.
  - Detective, The, 1968., (4to, 4 p.)
    Al Freeman, Jr. Bogle, p. 393: Freeman's performances well capture the mood and perspective of the 1960s activists and students: he's bright, committed, straightforward, a tad idealistic, but also almost sadly realistic.
  - Detective, The, 1968. British press book., (4to, 4 p.)
  - Devil and Max Devlin, The, 1981. Ad pad., (4to, 15 leaves)
  - Diamonds, 1975. Ad supplement., (Folio, 2 + 1 leaves)
  - Die Hard with a Vengeance, 1995. Japanese promotional booklet., (4to, 28 p.)
    Samuel L. Jackson.
  - Drum, 1976. British press book., (8vo, 4+2 p.)
  - Duel at Diablo, 1966. Press book., (Folio, 12 p.)
    Sidney Poitier. Bogle, p. 76: A routine Western with two surprises. First, Poitier shows up, decked out in fancy duds, playing a dandified cowboy, a horse dealer. Second, Poitier's color and his situation (a Black man in the Old West) have nothing to do with the movie's plot line.
  - Duel at Diablo, 1966. Advertising supplement., (Folio, 2 p.)
  - Earthquake, 1974. Press book., (8vo, 12 leaves)
    Richard Roundtree.
  - Ebony Ivory & Jade, 1976., (4to, 6 p.)
    Action film with female stars, one African-American, one Caucasian, and one Asian.
  - Edge of the City, 1957. Press book., (Folio, 8 p., copyright 1956)
    Sidney Poitier. Ruby Dee. Bogle, p. 77: With this taut, well-crafted, although misleading drama (a true liberal fantasy, if ever there was one), Poitier finally emerged as a star with one of his strongest yet oversimplified roles.
  - El Condor
    [see Condor, El]
  - Evil in the Deep, 1976., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Rosey Greer.
  - Final Comedown, The, 1972., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Billie Dee Williams playing the kind of movie militant that H. Rap Brown said, Can't do wrong right.
  - Five on the Black Hand Side, 1973. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Ja'net DuBois. Virginia Capers. Sonny Jim Gaines. Bogle, p. 83: One of the 1970s early new-style Black comedies, spotlighting the era's Black consciousness. Its theme: liberation.
  - Flying Ace, The, 1926., (Folio, 4 p.)
    A Black-cast aviation drama from the Norman Film Manufacturing Company.
  - For Love of Ivy, 1968. Press book., (4to, 4 p., 10 leaves)
    Sidney Poitier starred in this film; screenplay from an original story by Poitier. Bogle, p. 83-4: The gentle tone and fantasy-laden atmosphere (it's like a standard, well-made movie romance of the 1950s with all loose ends neatly tied up at the end) did not sit well with an audience anxious for grittier and more realistic Black films.
  - Fort Apache, The Bronx, 1981. British press book., (8vo, 8 p.)
  - Foxy Brown, 1974., (16 p.)
    Pam Grier. Bogle II, p. 252: Trash that Grier's movies were, her grit saved them.
  - From Nashville with Music, 1969., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Country and western musical film, racially integrated by the presence of singer Charley Pride.
  - Georgia, Georgia, 1972. Press book., (4to, 2 + 2 p.)
    Diane Sands. Script by Maya Angelou. Bogle, p. 89: Startling but uneven and rather frustrating drama focusing on a Black American pop star adrift while on tour in Stockholm...Touches on ground ripe for exploration: the Black star who is excepted not only to be an entertainer but also a spokeswoman for the problems and demands of the Black community.
  - Ghostbusters II, 1989. British press book., (8vo, 12 p.)
    Ernie Hudson.
  - Glory, 1989. Promotional book., (Folio, 20 leaves)
    Denzel Washington. Morgan Freeman. Andre Braugher. Sumptuously illustrated book on the film, printed in a small edition for circulation to major theater chains. Bogle II, p. 309: The story of the 54th Regiment, the first Black infantry in the North during the Civil War. It also bore the mark of well-intentioned filmmakers who still felt the need for built-in safeguards and points of identification for a white audience.
  - Glory, 1989. Broadsides., (4to, 4 items)
    Four broadsides used in the movie. Includes: "Proclamation... April 10, 1863" (2 copies); "The Enemy is Approaching;" and "Regulations for Camp Readville."
  - Going to Glory...Come to Jesus 1946. Lobby cards and bag., (Quarto, 9 items)
    Eight lobby cards used to advertise the movie in theater lobbies, along with the paper bag for the cards.
  - Gone with the Wind, 1939, reissued 1967. Press book, copyright 1974., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Hattie McDaniel.
  - Gone with the Wind [The Story of], 1939, reissued 1967. Theater souvenir program (covers loose), copyright 1967., (4to, 36 p.)
  - Gordon's War, 1973. Press book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Paul Winfield. Bogle, p. 96: [Winfield] portrays a Vietnam veteran returning home to New York to a dead wife, the victim of a drug overdose. Enlisting the aid of three other Viet vets, he becomes a vigilante, determined to rub out the dope dealers.
  - Gordon's War, 1973. Promotional brochure., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Grand Canyon, 1991. British press book., (8vo, 6 p.)
    Danny Glover.
  - Grasshopper, The, 1970. Advertising supplement., (Folio, 2 p.)
  - Grasshopper, The, 1970., (Folio, 19 p.)
    Bogle, p. 96: In a strange way, this is one of Jim Brown's most effective roles. He understands the plight of a Black man ill-at-ease in a high-powered world that sees him as a symbol of former glory--sadly, a symbol that can be bought.
  - Great White Hope, The, 1970. Press book., (4to, 8 p.)
    James Earl Jones. Bogle, p. 97: Jones played the larger-than-life, self-destructive boxer Jack Johnson, who bows to no man or woman.
  - Green-Eyed Monster, The, 1919.
    [See entry for Love Bug, The ( 1919)]
  - Guess Who's Coming to Dinner, 1969 reissue of 1967 film on double-bill with 1966 film To Sir, with Love., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Sidney Poitier.
  - Halls of Anger, 1970., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Calvin Lockhart. Bogle, p. 104.
  - Hammer, 1972., (Folio, 2 p.)
  - Heart is a Lonely Hunter, The, 1968. Pressbook., (Folio, 24 p.)
    Cicely Tyson in a Carson McCullers adaptation.
  - Heart is a Lonely Hunter, The, 1968. Special promotional flyer., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Hickey & Boggs, 1972., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Detective film, starred Bill Cosby with his costar from the I Spy television series of the 1960s, Robert Culp.
  - Hit!, 1973. Press book and merchandising manual., (Folio, 4 p. + 7 leaves)
    Billie Dee Williams. Richard Pryor. Bogle, p. 106-7.
  - Hit Man, 1972. Press book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Bernie Casey. Bogle, p. 107: Very much reflects some of the social/political nihilism that set in during this period of Vietnam and later Watergate.
  - Honky, 1971., (8vo, 6 p.)
    Brenda Sykes. Bogle, p. 111-2.
  - Hurry Sundown, 1967. Press book ad supplement, copyright 1966., (4to, 4 p.)
  - I Crossed the Color Line, 1966., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Max Julien.
  - I Escaped From Devil's Island, 1973. Press book., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Jim Brown.
  - In the Heat of the Night, 1967. Danish illustrated theater program., (12mo, 10 p.)
  - In the Heat of the Night, 1967. Special ad supplement., (Folio, 2 p.)
    Issued in conjunction with the film's winning two Oscars.
  - Incident, The, 1967. Press book., (4to, 8 leaves)
    Ruby Dee. Brock Peters.
  - Introducing Dorothy Dandridge, 1999., (8vo, 6 p.)
    Halle Berry in a made-for-Home Box Office bio of the legendary Dandridge.
  - Kenner, 1969. Press book., (Folio, 8 p.)
  - Kill Squad, 1981., (4to, 6 p.)
  - Klansman, The, 1974. Advertising booklet., (4to, 9 p.)
  - Klansman, The, 1974. Supplementary advertising sheets., (8vo, 4 broadsides)
- Film titles L-R (Box 3)
  - Lady Sings the Blues, 1972., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Diana Ross. Billy Dee Williams. Richard Pryor. Bogle II, p. 245-6: The movie was vastly entertaining and emerged as the screen's first full-fledged Black romantic melodrama. It did indeed treat its central character with respect.
  - Lady Sings the Blues, 1972. Advertising., (Folio, 6 leaves)
  - Lady Sings the Blues, 1972. Press book ad supplement, (Folio, 4 leaves)
  - Landlord, The, 1970., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Screenplay: William Gunn. Pearl Bailey. Diana Sands. Louis Gossett Jr. Bogle, p. 120-130: A little known, satiric comedy/drama. The unusual, perceptive screenplay is by Black writer Bill Gunn. Mistily realistic and gritty for its time, The Landlord focused on a wealthy young white lad, who buys a tenement building in the ghetto. One of the residents is a lovely, jittery young Black woman with whom he becomes romantically involved, although she's already married. When the woman's Black husband (Lou Gossett) learns of this relationship, his entire world seems to collapse right before him--and right before our eyes too. Gunn's script endowed the husband with a poignant dignity and a keen intelligence, and the explosion was so corrosively logical, yet so unexpected in its intensity, that it indeed inspired awe, pity, and fear.
  - Last of the Mobile Hot-Shots, 1969. Press book, copyright 1970., (Folio, 10 p.)
    Robert Hooks in a Tennesse Williams adaptation of The Seven Descents of Myrtle.
  - Learning Tree, The, 1969. Press book., (Folio, 22 p.)
    Director and producer: Gordon Parks. Bogle II, p. 226: When Warner Brothers signed him to adapt his book for the screen, Parks became the first Black man to direct a major American movie. He resensitized his audiences so that they experienced again the pain of being told to leave a restaurant because of their color. His film remains a lyrical and eloquent statement of the Black experience in America.
  - Learning Tree, The, 1969. Promotional flyer., (12mo, 4 p.)
  - Let No Man Write My Epitaph, 1960., (Folio, 8 p. + 2 p. advertising supplement)
    Ella Fitzgerald's first dramatic role, that of a nightclub singer in a Skid Row bar.
  - Liberation of L.B. Jones, The, 1970. Press book insert., (4to, 4 p.)
  - Liberation of L.B. Jones, The, 1970. Press book insert., (Folio, 2 p.)
    This press book insert was especially prepared for placement in Negro newspapers.
  - Liberation of L.B. Jones, The, 1970. Press book., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Yaphet Kotto. Bogle II, p. 233: Black audiences tended to ignore the film's nominal stars (Roscoe Lee Browne as a bourgeois tom, Lola Falana as his 'slutty' wife) in favor of the militant character played by Kotto, who, at the film's climax, threw a tough old Southern racist into a hay cropper. Interestingly, this press book had a separate advertising campaign specifically designated for Negro newspapers. [See previous entry]
  - Lifeboat, 1944. Danish souvenir program., (12mo, 8 p.)